Guide to the German celebratory verse (Gelegenheitsdichtung): collection, 1550-1750
Department of Special Collections
German celebratory verse (Gelegenheitsdichtung): collection,
1550-1750
M1027
.75 linear ft. (140 pieces)
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
These poems celebrate marriages, funerals, births, farewells, New Years, inaugurations and installations, and fests and feasts. The collection concentrates on Lower Saxony in the era of George I, elector of Hanover and King of England. An indication of the many-layered culture of this society is the welter of languages used in these tracts. There are verses in French, Italian, Greek, Hebrew, Dutch, and Niederdeutsch, in addition to Latin and German. The French verses date from the reign of George I, who was inclined to imitate the court of Louis XIV. One of the Niederdeutsch poems is a burlesque on a betrothal, indicating that the Low German dialect was considered appropriate for joking and ribald humor. Many typefaces were used; many of the works were printed on the first presses of a particular city. At Lüneburg there was no press before 1616; this town is represented by five manuscripts.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions on access.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Bennett Gilbert, 1989.
Provenance
Purchased from Bennett Gilbert, 1989.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
This collection of German celebratory verse (Gelegenheitsdichtung) comprises 140 pieces, every one of very great rarity. Their rarity symbolizes the fragmented and disparate state of German literature between the end of the Renaissance, about 1550 in Germany, and the beginning of the creation of a national literature, after 1750. Between these two impulses German literature developed in uncommon genres that were deeply fertile in succeeding ages. Celebratory verse is one of these. The initial impulse of German humanism was expressed in the circle of neo-Latin writers centered in Nuremberg and in the universities of Tubingen and Erfurt. Speaking broadly, we may say that this energy was largely absorbed by the Reformation and diverted from literature to religion. With the exception of Frischlin and a few other dramatists, only philologists at work on Greek grammars and concordances represented the humane letters in the last half of the century. After about 1750, German literature began its greatest period. The French influence, the growing prosperity of the large towns, and Germany's indigenous traditions prepared the way on which Goethe above all and many others created Germany's national literature for the first time in a European context. In between these two eras lay a different and yet classic Germany.
It was a land of over 300 separate territories, each identifying with its own, separate, intimately held, and jealously defended privileges, customs, rights, and laws. Time honored each of these communities by long and rich traditions, whether ruled by archbishop, count, prince or king, or a free town or imperial city. The institution of the Empire had really ceased to matter from about 1600: every effort of the Emperor displayed his weakness, and the Diet was an assembly of ambassadors who never debated and mostly waited for instructions from their sovereigns. It was a poor country, struggling for nearly a century to overcome the devastation of the Thirty Years War. In this environment, literature in Germany lacked a national style and national subjects, just as Germany itself had no capital and no uniform system of weights and measures. Thus the development of a national literature has been called "the almost miraculous creation of a soul without a body". This marvellous effort was sustained in isolation and poverty in the period from 1550 to 1750 through several literary and channels, gathering strength in circumstances free of a dominant "taste: and of critical convention. One of the most important of these was the genre of celebratory verse. In it, as in the picaresque novel, or the brilliant Baroque poetry of the seventeenth century, one finds the complex and flavorful life of the Germans. These poems celebrate marriages, funerals, births, farewells, New Years, inaugurations and installations, and fests and feasts. Thus each poem is a memento for us of a circumstance or an event that is rich in color, full of aspirations and struggles. The verse leaflets in this collection show a full range of the religious, political, and social textures of the times and are, in spite of their ephemerality, indispensable documents of this history. This collection concentrates on Lower Saxony in the era of George I, elector of Hanover and King of England. The deep observation of this place and time made possible by this collections shows the strength and weakness of German society and literature in this period:long blood ties and intimate geographical relationships that bound the communities and the region strongly together and at the same time fostered a provincial rather than a national loyalty. Saxony mirrored the political complexity of Germany. For centuries, including and especially the seventeenth century, there was a dizzying barter exchange of these communities from one princely hand to another. Ulneberg, an important town in the 1500's, was, with Celle, perhaps the most frequently traded. Similarly, the towns of the area of Braunschweig represent the most culturally rich and produàtive area of Germany in the late seventeenth century. Thus the collection exactly centers on the most interesting example of a typical state.
An indication of the many-layered culture of this society is the welter of languages used in these tracts. There are verses in French, Italian, Greek, Hebrew, Dutch, and Niederdeutsch, in addition to Latin and German. The French verses date from the reign of George I, who was inclined to imitate the court of Louis XIV. One of the Niederdeutsch poems is a burlesque on a betrothal, indicated that the Low German dialect was considered appropriate for joking and ribald humor. The use of these languages gave rise to the use of many typefaces. The collections includes works from the first press at Helmstedt with specimens of its Greek typeface; later, a considerable amount of classical philology was printed there. At Luneburg there was no press before 1616, so that this town is represented by five sixteenth-century manuscripts of celebratory verse. Many of the works printed by the first presses in Uelzen, Helmstedt, Wittenberg, and Hannover concern Lilneberg families, who went to these neighbouring towns for what their own city could not supply. It is that kind of story which makes this collection a singular resource. By concentrating on Lower Saxony, a culturally and historically rich part of Germany that suffered more than anywhere else in the Thirty Years War, it makes it possible to learn many stories of the lives of its people. The relationships of families, attitudes toward events, the whole structure of friendship and association are, from a sociological point of view, revealed in these verses. They show in an unguarded moment the power structure of the day. This period also saw the final separation of Hanoverian territory from Saxony, so that we are able to glimpse the royal court at Hannover at a great period in its history, c. 1680-1730. Leibniz was the greatest figure here, and some of the verses celebrate his friends and associates, such as Gerhardt Molanus and Rudolf Wagner. Some had relied on Leibniz for academic promotions or corresponded for him on philosophical matters. One pamphlet concerns Nicolaus Förster, the court book dealer; another, Hermann von der Hardt, librarian to Rudolf August von Braunschweig. Because of the rarity of such leaflets and broadsides as these, they remain a relatively new source for the study of life and literature. Like the old town statute books re-discovered by the recent French historians, these gently uncover the intimate life of places long ago and far away, revealing to us the reality of that life. It is in this connection that we return to the literary importance of celebratory verse. This genre was a format in which ordinary people could write creatively for everyday use. These are precisely the opposite of literature for literature's sake: they are practical literature, for people celebrating and ornamenting the great events of ordinary life. The pace of life in Germany was slow, and literary composition was very individualistic, even eccentric. For this reason we find acrostics, chronograms, anagrams, and puns throughout these texts. Thus celebratory verse was the acceptable, available, and inevitable channel in which German literature flowed during these difficult centuries. Because of this the genre will play an important role in the expanding study of Baroque German rhetoric and critical theory. It was a part of contemporary discourse in which almost anyone could practise his compositional skills. Works such as W. Barner's important Barok Rhetorik have already begun to take it into account. Rudolf Lenz has devoted a great deal of attention to German funeral orations, resulting in catalogues of the collections in Marburg and Giessen. It is thus of great importance to assemble and to hold catalogued collections. Within Germany, many of these texts are unknown: of the ill imprints from Lower Saxony, only 15 are to be found in the most comprehensive bibliography. Leibniz is the most intensively studied figure of the period, and yet the poem he wrote for his ailing patron is unrecorded in this form, its first appearance in print. None of the sixteenth century imprints is in the British Library; very few, if any, of the 140 titles are in the National Union Catalogue. The many social and literary implications of these texts are an instance of one of the very good reasons for collecting early printed matter: the power of that body of material to inform us not only about the creative geniuses, the text of whose works is safe, but the other 99%, the real stuff of history. The developments essential to the explosive growth of German literature after 1750 are found in the celebratory verse and other genres of the preceding period, which came not fronm literary theory but from the heart. They thus define for us the context in which the German faced the cosmpolitan influences of.the Enlightenment. They are evidence of the fertility of German culture in this stressful and difficult period, showing how literature survived on the strength of the culture, the close-knit and communal character of German life. It is these details and glories of a consequential period of German literary and social history that poetry of this genre recalls for us, setting the stage for the great poetry of Germany's neoclassical and romantic periods.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
German literature--Early modern, 1500-1700.; German poetry--Early modern, 1500-1700.; Germany--Religious life and customs--Modern period, 1517-
Collection Contents
- COTHENIUS, Bartholdus, et al. Nuptiis ... Bertholdi Snelli ... et Margaretae, reverendi & clarissimi yin Dn. M. Barthodi Volkerlingii. Braunschweig, Duncker,1627., 001; Small 4to, 6 11.
  Collection of poems celebrating the wedding of Berthold Snell and Margarete Voickerling from 18 well-wishers, including brothers of the bride and groom.
- BUTEMEISTER, Johann Julius. Als der wol-ehrwtirdige .. Johann Christoph Wahrendorff ... mit ... Catharina Johanna Erythropelin ... sein Hochzeits-Festin celebrirte. Braunschweig, Johann Georg Zilliger, 1710., 002.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem on the wedding of Johann Christian Wahrendorff and Catharina Johanna Erythropel.
- L., F. Der durchlauchtigsten nutritorum kluge Sorgfalt.Braunschweig, Arnold Jacob Keitel, 1717., 003.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem in praise of Jonas Conrad Schramme on his appointment as professor of theology at Helmstedt, mentioning many of his colleagues and academic predecessors.
- (KOBERG-ERYTHROPEL]. Die gesegnete Weisheit. Celle, Andreas Hoiwein,n.d., 004.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Bernhard Heinrich Koberg and Sophia Erythropel, daughter of David Rupert Erythropel.
- ZEDELIUS, Joachim Daniel. Wohlgemeintes Neu-Jahrs- und Hochzeit-Praesent. Clausthal, [Jacob Wilke], 1716., 005.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Lattmann and Wissel. Jacob Wilke was the first and, at the time, only printer in Clausthal. Grotefend c5.
- [KONIG, Joh. Ulrich]. Bey dem Muller- und Hartmannischen Hochze.it-Feste. Dresden, Johann Conrad Stassel, 1726., 006.; Folio, 2 11.
  A contemporary manuscript notation on the title-page attributes this poem to Johann Ulrich Konig on the wedding of Muller, a fellow poet, and Hartmann. K~nig, a poet and composer of opera, came to Dresden as poet to the royal court of Saxony from Hamburg where, moving in literary and musical circles, he had already composed a number of pastorals, serenades, comedies, oratorios, and pieces of musical theatre. At Dresden he also became master of ceremonies, and he further developed his interest in, and became a major proponent of, Lustspiele in German, reacting to the preference for foreign languages and arts at court. ADB 16, 516-18.
- HOMMEL, Johann Michael. Die unter des Himmels Gnaden-blicken mit erwünschtem Gl~ick und tausenfroher Wonne h~chstvergnügend herfürstrahlende Geburts- und Nahmens-Sonne. Erfurt, Muller, 1705., 007.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the birthday of Lothar Franz von Schonborn, archbishop of Mainz. As archbishop Lothar Franz undertook several architectural projects, some grandiose, one of which was the construction of a fountain, the Neuer Brunnen; it is referred to in the poem. ADB 32, 277.
- LAUTER.BACH, Christof Heinrich, et al. Logoi Propemytikoi. [Halberstadt], Johann Erasmus Hynitzsch, 1676., 008.; Small 4to, 2 11.
  Poems wishing Petrus Pax farewell as he leaves the Johannisschule in Halberstadt for the priesthood. Written by his colleagues such asLauterbach, rector of the school (Jocher/Adelung 3, 1419), and students.
- GLEISSENBERGK, Matthias, et al. Bona verba & pia vota. Halberstadt, Johann Erasmus Hynitzsch, 1677., 009.; Small 4to, 8 11.
  Collection of poems in Latin and German celebrating the wedding of Petrus Pax and Anna Margareta Niepagen. Among the 18 authors are Christoph H. Lauterbach, Pax's former colleague at the Johannisschule, and Cotfriedt Gengenbach, a noted lawyer who also wrote a history of Magdeburg(Jocher/Adelung 2, 1394).
- TELEMANN, Tobias, et al. Strenae calendis. Halberstadt, Johann Erasmus Hynitzsch, 1677., 010.; Small 4to, 4 11.
  Collection of 30 poems in Greek, Latin and German addressed to Michael Wurtzler, rector of the Lyceum in Halberstadt. One of the authors, Jacob Ludeke went on to become mayor of Calbe. Jocher/Ade1urig 3, 115.
- (FORSTER, Nicolaus]. Hertzliches Vergnügen über den wiederum glücklich erlebten Naniens-Tag Herrn Herrn Nicolai Försters. [Halberstadt], mit Detleffsischen Schrifften, 1729., 011.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem marking the 73rd birthday of Nicolaus Forster, bookdealer at the royal court in Hannover who supplied Leibniz with books for the ducal library, written by Forster's grandson.Linke, p. 109.
- (BLOCH]. Gamelia in honorem nuptialem docti juxta ac humani yin D. Pauli Blocii. Hamburg, Heinrich Binder, 1595., 012.; Small 4to, 8 11.
  Collection of poems celebrating the wedding of Paul Bloch and Margaretha Dutzenrad. Not in Kayser-Dehn.
- HEMELING, Johann. Ode Jambica oder glückwünschendes Ehrenlied. Hannover, Georg Fniedrich Grimme, 1660., 013.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Moritz Duven and Margaretha Peters.
- MEIER Henning Jacob. Nuptiis auspicatissimis. Hannover, Johann Peter Grimme, 1694., 015.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the marriage of Johann Lorentz Brockniann and AnnaElisabeth Bahmer, sister of the noted scholars Justus Chnistoph andPhillip Ludwig Bahmer.
- W., E.G.S.v. Hertzinniglicher Wunsch. Hannover, Johann Peter Grimme, .1695, 016.; Broadside.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Friedrich Adolph Hoysen and Sophia Elisabeth Moithan. Hoysen, appointed pastor at Kreuzkirche in Hannover the year before his marriage, was one of a long line of pastorè in the family. Roter.: Hann. 2, 422.
- W., C. Woilgemeintes Schetz- und G1ückwüiinschungs-Gedicht auff das hochzeit].iche Ehren-Fest. Hannover, Johann Peter Gnimme, 1699., 017.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem on the wedding of Johann Heinriich Grupe and Catharina Sophi Westerman. Grupe had become pastor at Stemmen the year before his marriage.
- [LANGSCHMID, Leven B.]. Nachdem der hoch-ehrwürdige ... Laevin Burchard Langschmid ... das neu anvertraute Ampt angetreten hatte. Hannover, Samuel Ammon, 1706., 018.; Folio, 2 11.
  Verses written for the musical evening welcoming Langschmid as pastor to the Hanoverian court~ Parts are specified for alto, chorus, tenor, bass and cantus.
- SCHORKOP, J.G. and F.J. Bey der Seeligerschen und Schôrkopschen Hochzeit. [Hannover], 1709., 019.; Folio, 2 11.
  Sonnet and aria celebrating the marriage of Seeliger and Schórkop, written by the bride's brothers.
- HEIMANN, David Christoph. Als der ... Johann Christoph Wahrendorff mit Catharina Johanna ... semen hochzeitlichen Ehren-Tag beging.Hannover, J.D. Amnion, 1710., 020.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Johann Christian Wahrendorff and Catharina Johanna Erythropel, the daughter of David Rupert Erythropel.
- SCHMIDT, Johann Andreas. Als der hoch-wohl-ehrwürdige ... Johan. Christoph. Wahrendorf, ... mit ... Cathar. Johanna Erythropilin ... sein erfreuliches Ehe-fest feyerte. [Hannover?], 1710., 021.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem on the wedding of Johann Christoph Wahrendorff and Catharina Johanna Erythropel, written by a young Schmidt, son of the abbot of Marienthal.
- [WAHRENDORFF- ERYTHROPEL]. Einige gluckwiinschende Gedariken. Hannover, Holwein, 1710., 022.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the marriage of Johann Christoph Wahrendorff and Catharina Johanna Erythropel.
- AUGSPURG, Andreas Christoph. Ara piae devotionis ac submissae venerationis ... Cerhardo, liberi & imperialis coenobii Luccensis Abbati. Hannover, Typis Holweinii, [1715]., 023.; Folio, 4 11.
  This long poem for the New Year honouring Gerhardt Wolter Molanus, abbot of Loccum and head of the ecclesiastical court at Hannover, makes special mention of his great library and collection of rare coins, incorporating the motto which was inscribed above the entrance to each: Fructus sancti coelibatus. Part of the library went to the Royal Library at Hannover where a catalogue was issued in 1729; another part went to C~ttingen. Molanus, formerly a professor of mathematics and theology before succeeding his brother-in-law Johann Kotzebue as abbot in 1677, was a close friend of Leibniz and facilitated many debates, notably that between Leibniz and the Cartesian Arnold Eckhard. Together they worked on bringing about a reunion of Catholics and Protestants in Loccum. The supportive collaboration between the two men on many issues, both private and public, continued throughout their lives. ADB 22, 86-9. Written by the reform-minded rector of the Lyceum in Hannover. Roter.: Hann. 1, 65.
- BLUMEYER, Johann Heinrich. Das geseegnate Bussmannische Haus ... an dem Bussmannischen und Turckischen Ehren- und Hochzeit-Feste. Hannover, gedruckt mit Holweinischen Schriften, 1715., 024.; Folio, 2 11.
  Heading the long poem celebrating the marriage of Anton Julius Bussmann and Anna Agnesa Tuerck is a chronogram. Bussmann was the son of a noted Hannover medical doctor. Roter,: Hann. 1, 328.
- EGGERS, Georg Nicolaus. Als der wol-edle, vest und gross-achtbahre Herr, Herr Conrad Rabe ... sein Jubileum Gamicum feyerlich beging und an demselben Tage seine geliebte Jungfer Enckelin ... verniahlt wurde. [Hannover?], 1720., 025.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating both the 50th wedding anniversary of Conrad Rabe, brewer in Hannover, and his wife, Margaretha Catharina, n~e Funcke, and also the marriage of their granddaughter, Hedwig Dorothea Catharina Rabe,and Justus Ludolph Vietje. The bride's father and Conrad's son, Johann Rabe, was pastor at St. Aegidien in Hanriover. Written by Eggers as a theology student before he became archdeacon at Nikolaikirche in Lüneburg.Roter.: Hann. 1, 523.Linke, p. 283; Roth 9, R8210 lists another poem on this same occasion.
- [ERYTHROPEL-KOTZEBUE]. Die zwar ausser priestlichen Stande doch aus priestlichem Stanim hochst glücklich-getroffene Ehe-Verbindung, solten an dam Erythropelschen und Kotzebuischen Hochzeit-Festin. [Hannover], 1722., 026.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Erythropel and Sophia Amalia Kotzebue, grand-daughter of Johann Kotzebue, former abbot of Loccum. Linke, p. 100.
- WEIDEMANN, M.J.H. Der Segen Gottes uber das Geschlecht der Froinmen bey dem Erythropelisch- und Kotzebuischen Hochzeits-Festin. Hannover,1722., 027.; Folio, 2 11.
  Sonnet celebrating the wedding of Sophia Amalia Kotzebue and Erythropel. Linke, p. 100.
- BLUMEYER, Johann Heinrich. Die blühende Fruhlings-lust ... bay dem Haussmannischen- und Rabenschen Hochzeit-Festin. Hannover, 1723., 028.; Folio, 2 11.
  Long poem honouring the wedding of Johann Ernest Haussman and Christiana Louise Rabe, daughter of Johann Rabe, pastor at St. Aegidien in Hannover, written by a highly reputed academic and theologian. Blumeyer had been private tutor to the mayor's children before becoming Conrektor at the Altst~dter-Schule in Hannover. Jacher/Adelung 1, 1930.
- RABE, David Conrad. Die geseegnete Hausmannische Haushaltung. Hannover, 1723., 029.; Broadside.
  Announcement and celebratory sonnet on the wedding of Johann Ernest Haussman and Christiana Louise Rabe, written by the bride's brother, later pastor in D~ren, Wülffel and Hannover.
- GEVERDS, Karsten. Einfäldige doch wolgemeinde Glückwunsch up dat Bielager. Hannover, 1724., 030.; Folio, 2 11. (2 copies)
  Poem in Niederdeutsch on the wedding of Ernst August von Billow and Sophie Charlotte von Platen. Linke, p. 52; Borchling-Claussen 4051.
- FLUGGE, H. Pietas privata. [Hannover], Literis Holweinii, 1725., 031.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem honouring Christian Ulrich Grupen on acceding to the mayoral office of Hannover. As mayor, Grupen made such vast improvements in the city's archives and registers that after forty years of service, Hannover thanked him with a sizeable financial gift. Grupen also gave his large private library to the Oberappellationsgericht in Celle with money for its support. Roter.: Hann. 1, 190-5. Written by the senior pastor of Georgenkirche. Rater.: Hann. 1, 48. Linke, p. 132.
- BLUMEYER, Johann Heinrich. Als in dem Hannoverschen Cana Christian Ulrich Grupen, ... ibm die ... Jungfer Catharina Dorothea Drosten ... antrauen hess. Hannover, Ludoiph Heine, 1726., 032.; Folio, 4 11.
  Long poem celebrating the marriage of Grupen and Droste. Grupen, a friend of Leibniz and later famous for his Origines and Antiquitates, became mayor of Hannover the year before his marriage. The poem is filled with religious and some classical references which are all duly footnoted. One footnote is to Aegidius Hunnius, a contemporary leading Lutheran orthodox in Helmstedt. Linke, p. 132.
- CORBER, F.H. Gratulatio post festuin. Hannover, gedruckt mit Heinischen Schrifften, 1726., 033.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Johann Heinrich Redeker and Dorothea Elisabeth Gr~fen. The bride was the widow of A.C. Augspurg, a former learned schoolmaster and writer of occasional verse. Roter.: Hann. I,65.
- DROSTE, V.G. Die Furtrefflichkeit der Liebe. Hannover, Ludoiph Heine, 1726., 034.; Folio, 2 11.
  Poem celebrating the wedding of Christian Ulrich Grupen and Catharina Dorothea Droste.
- ENGEL, Johann B. Die Liebe, als em Feuer. [Hannover], 1726., 035.; Folio, 2 11.